Finding Aid for Robert M. Slusser research files,ca. 1940-ca. 1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert M. Slusser research files ca. 1940-ca. 1980
Slusser, Robert M., 1916-
13 linear feet (21 boxes).
89362 Aa 2
Professor of Russian and Soviet history at Michigan State University. Research and bibliographic note cards used in his study and teaching of Russian history, particularly relating to the study of the Soviet Union; also publications and dissertation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Slusser (donor no. 7387 ) and came to the library in 1987 and 1995.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Robert M. Slusser was a distinguished scholar of Russian history. Born May 14, 1916, Slusser was educated at the University of Chicago (A.B., 1941) and Columbia University (M.A., 1960 and Ph.D., 1963). He taught at Johns Hopkins and Columbia University before coming to Michigan State University in 1970. He retired from MSU some time in the mid-1980s. Slusser's particular area of expertise was modern Russian history. In particular, he devoted much of his research to Soviet foreign policy and to the study of the Soviet secret police. Slusser wrote many books and articles on these areas of Russian history.
The Slusser collection consists primarily of research and bibliographic note cards produced as a result of his study of Russian history and used in his classes and in the preparation of his books and articles. There are in addition a series of copies of his articles and reviews.
Subjects:
Russia--History.; Russia--Study and teaching.; Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union--Study and teaching.
- Bibliographical/research note cards
  - Chronological notes
    - 1903-1917 (Box 12)
    - 1918-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1984 (Box 4)
  - 1905 revolution bibliography (Box 5)
  - Laos notes/bibliography (Box 5)
  - Secret police
    - Biographies (Box 6)
    - Bibliography, A-S (Box 7)
    - Bibliography, T-Z (Box 8)
    - Bibliography (general) (Box 8)
    - Laws and decrees (Box 8)
  - Disarmament (Box 8)
  - USSR bibliography (Box 9)
    - A-S (Box 9)
    - S-V (Box 10)
  - 1957-1964 bibliography (Box 10)
  - Berlin (since 1945) (Box 10)
  - 1917 bibliography (Box 11)
  - Miscellanea (Box 11)
  - Foreign policy (Box 12)
  - World War II (Box 12)
  - Dissidents/samizdat (Box 12)
  - Biographies, A-P (Box 13)
  - Biographies, R-Z (Box 14)
  - Kennedy/JFK assassination (Box 14)
  - Russia (origins to 1917) (Box 15)
  - Far East (Box 15)
  - Cuba (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Research notes (various) (Box 17)
  - Research notes (Box 18)
  - Clippings (Box 18)
  - Lists (Box 18)
- Other materials
  - Reviews, articles, etc. (Box 19)
  - Reviews, articles, etc. (Box 20)
  - Reviews, articles, etc. (Box 21)
  - Dissertation (Box 21)
  - Diary, 1953-1955 (Box 21)